Guide to the Norman Guttman Papers, 1952-1982
University Archives Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Norman Guttman papers 1952-1982
University Archives, Duke University
Guttman, Norman, 1920-.
1.5 Linear Feet 850 Items
Dr. Norman Guttman taught in the Department of Psychology from 1951 until his death in 1984.
The collection contains correspondence from 1952-1982.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Norman Guttman Papers were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1984.
Biographical Note
Norman Guttman was born October 17, 1920 in Minneapolis, Minnesota. He married Renate Pawel on February 6, 1948. He received his B. A. degree in 1942 from the University of Minnesota and his Ph.D. from Indiana University in 1951. He came to Duke soon after earning his Ph.D. and began teaching in the Dept. of Psychology. Dr. Guttman was Director of Graduate Studies in Psychology from 1963-1964 and 1965-1967. He was also active in curricular reform at Duke. His chief interests were learning stimulus generalization, conditioning, motivation, and the history of psychology. He died in April 1984.
Collection Overview
Contains a mixture of personal, political and professional correspondence, the latter being usually scholarly in nature, with some evaluations of grant proposals and recommendations. The folder on the Nixon Library controversy contains correspondence and printed matter, with a few petitions and name-and-address blanks from contributors to the opposition to the Library, in which Guttman was instrumental. The collection ranges in date from 1952-1982.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Duke University. Faculty.
Duke University. Dept. of Psychology.
Related Material
News Service Biographical Files, 1960-2004.
University Archives. Duke University.
Biographical Reference Files, 1972-2004.
University Archives. Duke University.
Department of Psychology Records.
University Archives. Duke University.
Contents of Collection
- Container List, 1 Box
  - Correspondence Received, 1952-1953, 1961-1962 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence Sent, 1952, 1956-1957
  - Correspondence, 1962-1964 (2 folders)
  - Correspondence, 1964-1967
  - Correspondence, 1970-1971
  - Correspondence, 1971-1973
  - Correspondence, 1974-1976
  - Correspondence, 1977-1978
  - Correspondence, 1978-1980
  - Correspondence, 1980-1982 June
  - Nixon Library Materials, Correspondence, 1981-1982